When a person has extreme social anxiety,
所谓的“交流障碍症” 是指不擅长和人交流的一种症状
they struggle to communicate with others.
或是指有这种症状的人
They might get to know someone under special circumstances,
例如和在特殊情况下变要好的人
then meet them again after a break…
再度过假日后再次碰面时…
If I greet her enthusiastically and she reacts coolly like, "Oh, hi," then what?
如果我热情地跟她打招呼 她却回应得很冷淡的话该怎么办？
But it would be weird to ignore her completely…
但回避对方又会很不自然…
Our eyes met and she looked away!
刚才明明就跟她对上眼神 她却马上避开！
In this way…
更准确地说…
I want to talk to her but I don't know how!
我不知道要怎么跟她搭话！
That's how it is.
正处于这种状况
A…
上…
-Agari! -Eek!
-上理！ -请说！
Here's… that novel we talked about on the field trip.
这本…是校外教学时提过的那本小说
Oh!
这样啊！
You brought it for me!
你特地帮我带来了啊！
Thank you so much!
谢谢你！
Yes. You may thank me.
没错 你就好好感谢我吧
Get your cringey Chrysanthemum Blade of Darkness back?
你拿回那根可笑的 暗黑菊一文字了吗？
Don't say cringey!
“可笑”是多余的！
Huh? Did you phone by yourself?
是喔 那你是自己 打电话要回来的吗？
-O-Of course I did! -PARENTS CALLED
-这点小事才难不倒我！ -（请爸妈打的）
CHATTER
（喋喋不休）
Wow, this is great, Inaka!
是喔 你好厉害喔 井中！
Did you make this?
这是你自己做的吗？
It's so cute!
好可爱喔！
Y-You don't mind?
不会造成你们的困扰吗？
Huh? Why would I? I'm so happy!
什么？怎么会？我很开心喔
-Thank you very much! -Hey, he's here!
-非常谢谢你！ -喂 他来了！
APPEARS
（出现）
Makoto Katai has come to school.
-片居诚来学校了 -喂 他来了！
T-Today I will say good morning to everyone, for sure!
我今天一定要跟大家道早安！
Good morning, Katai.
早安 片居同学
Oh! Tadano! He's so kind!
天啊！只野同学好温柔！
Katai, sir! Good morning!
片居同学！早安！
Hey, Katai.
喂 片居
The other day, your body was pretty great.
上次你的肉体真的太棒了
THE CLASS HOMOPHILES
（班上的腐女们）
I'll give you some photos.
对了 我会把照片给你
You should hand out the art from that day.
你也该把那天的艺术照发出去
Alright, see you later.
那就待会见
Yeah, later.
好 晚点见
NORMAL MODE
（正常模式）
NEGATIVE MODE
（悲观模式）
-IT WILL SOMEHOW WORK OUT MODE -POMPH!
（船到桥头自然直模式 振作！）
SECOND NEGATIVE MODE
（第二阶段悲观模式）
She's not going for it…
她还是不过去啊…
Komi?
古见同学？
Oh, uh, good mor--
那个 早…
GOOD MORNING.
（早安）
That's pretty interesting. Talking with a notebook.
用笔记本对话果然很有趣呢
Good morning, Komi.
早安 古见同学
It just sort of tickles me.
这好像戳中我的笑点了
-Oh, sorry. -Okay!
-抱歉 我过去一下 -好！
Good morning!
早安！
Meanwhile, Tadano had a lot on his mind.
同一时间在脑海中 产生各种想法的只野同学
LUNCH TIME
（午休时间）
That reminds me. Komi?
话说回来 古见同学
Any Valentine's Day plans?
你情人节有什么计划吗？
GLANCE
（偷瞄）
-NOTHING YET. -That was a pretty big pause.
-（还没决定） -刚才停顿了一下呢
Okay. Want to come over and make something today?
那你今天要不要来我家一起做？
I make treats for my family every year.
我每年都会做要给家人的份
Wouldn't it be fun if we made them together?
机会难得 找朋友一起做也比较有趣吧
NOD
（点头）
Alright, let's do it.
好 就这样决定了
Me too…
我也可以…
Can I come too?
一起去吗？
Oh, yeah, come!
好啊 一起来吧！
Sorry Tadano. Today it's a girls party.
抱歉了 只野 今天是女生的聚会
Oh, I, uh… I didn't want to go anyway.
什么？我并没有特别想去啊
BUT HE WAS LISTENING IN.
（但他一直在偷听）
Okay, here we are!
好 我们到了！
I'm home!
我回来了！
Kids, always scattering everything around.
那些家伙鞋子又脱得乱七八糟的
Hey sis, welcome home!
姐姐 你回来了啊！
Kaede too! C'mon in!
也欢迎枫姐姐来玩！
Pardon me…
打扰了…
Hey, what do you want to pla…
我问你 今天我们要玩什…
FROZEN
（静止）
KAZUYA ONEMINE (AGE 6)
（尾根峰和也 6岁）
NANA ONEMINE (AGE 6)
（尾根峰奈奈 6岁）
NONO ONEMINE (AGE 3)
（尾根峰乃乃 3岁）
SHOKO KOMI (AGE 17)
（古见硝子 17岁）
SMACK!
（拍打）
Those are my little siblings.
那些是我的弟弟跟妹妹
The four of them are a handful, but don't mind them.
有四个人 可能有点碍事 但就请你跟他们好好相处了
-Alright, let's make this! -CHOCOLATE CAKE
-好 那要来做啦！ -（巧克力蛋糕）
POMPH!
（干劲十足）
Komi, melt the chocolate and butter in the double boiler.
那就请古见同学 隔水加热巧克力跟奶油
Kaede, sift the flour and cocoa powder.
枫则把面粉跟可可粉过筛
EGG WHITE, EGG YOLK
（蛋白 蛋黄）
APPLAUSE
（拍手）
It's not such a big deal.
这没什么了不起的啦
-CREAM, BRANDY, YOLKS, SUGAR -Heat this, and add sugar.
-（鲜奶油 白兰地 蛋黄加砂糖） -同样隔水加热 加入砂糖
Then the cream and brandy.
另外加鲜奶油跟白兰地
Now add the chocolate we melted earlier.
接着把刚才融化的巧克力也加进去
Now we'll make the meringue!
好！要来做蛋白霜了！
FLUFFY
（软绵）
-Please be yummy. -RATTLE RATTLE
-要变好吃喔 -（搅拌）
It'll take a week at this rate.
照这个速度花一个礼拜也做不完吧
-We'll help too! -Yeah!
-我们也来帮忙！ -来帮忙！
Okay, wash your hands!
好 那去洗手！
-Go! Go! Go! Go! -SQUISH SQUISH
-看我的！ -（大力搅拌）
KOMI IS FEELING ANXIOUS.
（坐立难安的古见同学）
Komi, why don't you help them out?
古见同学也去帮他们吧
I'll take care of this.
这边我会负责弄好
Hey, my arms are tired!
姐姐 我的手酸了！
It isn't whipped enough, is it? Keep going!
还没起泡吧？还要继续打发！
WHIP WHIP
（迅速搅拌）
Wow!
好强喔！
Scary lady, you're amazing!
可怕的大姐姐好厉害！
SCARY?!
（可怕？）
You can do it!
加油
-You can do it! -Me next!
-加油！ -下一个换我！
You can do it!
加油！
FLUFFY
（松软绵密）
It's perfect!
很完美！
Yay!
太好了！
Okay, next…
那么接下来…
we add a little meringue and stir.
加一点蛋白霜进去后搅拌
Then add the sifted flour and cocoa powder.
再加入过筛完的面粉跟可可粉
Mix in the meringue in thirds.
接下来要把蛋白霜分三次加进去混合
Alright.
好了
-Now we bake it for fifty minutes. -THEY SNUCK A TASTE.
-因为要烤50分钟… -（偷吃的两个人）
Now we have fifty minutes to play!
接下来的50分钟 请姐姐们陪你们玩吧！
Yay!
好耶！
Once upon a time…
从前从前…
in a land far away…
在某个地方…
Hey scary lady, why don't you talk?
可怕的姐姐为什么不说话？
STAB
（受打击）
I want to know too!
我也很在意那一点！
It's because she's shy. Don't pester her too much!
因为那位姐姐很害羞 不能欺负她喔！
Shaa?
“阿羞”？
Not shaa.
不是“阿羞”
Okay, say "Ah!" Say "Ah!"
那么你说说看“啊！”
Ah!
啊！
Say "Ah! Ah!"
说说看“啊！”
Ah…
啊…
SUDDENLY NOT INTERESTED
（突然没兴趣了）
I wonder if the cake rose!
不知道蛋糕膨起来了没
Let's go see! Shaa lady!
我们去看！阿羞姐姐！
Wow! It rose! It rose!
天啊 膨起来了！
Wow!
好棒喔
Yeah!
对啊
Hey, shaa lady.
我说阿羞姐姐你啊
You have a nice voice, so you should talk more!
声音这么好听 多说一点话比较好喔！
Yeah!
就是啊！
I… I'll try.
我会加油的
Okay everyone, sit down!
好了 大家坐下来！
We're going to eat this piping hot chocolate cake!
要来吃刚出炉 热烘烘的巧克力蛋糕了！
Yay!
好耶！
-We did a really good job! -Yes, we did!
-我们做得很成功耶！ -就是说啊！
Here!
来！
Komi.
古见同学
How is it? Good?
怎么样啊？好吃吗？
POMPH
（点头）
Yay!
太好了！
-So sweet! -It's really good!
-好甜喔！ -很好吃呢！
Huh? What's that?
等等 那是什么？
-You can have some too! -Lucky!
-你也来吃吧！ -太幸运了！
Good for you!
真是太好了 哥哥！
Oh. We ate it all.
糟了 全都吃掉了耶
Sorry.
抱歉啦
YOU'RE MAKING A LOT!
（你要做很多啊）
Romance.
“恋爱”
It can't be detached from everyday life.
是不管怎样都没办法 跟人生切割开来的东西
Even girls who are normally timid,
即使是平时表现矜持的女性
are allowed to approach the person they like on this day.
在这天也被允许向喜欢的人搭话
The girls get excited and the boys get nervous.
女生们紧张兴奋 男生们坐立不安
Yes, today is…
没错 今天就是…
-A DAY OF INTERSECTING EXPECTATIONS -Valentine's Day!
-（一年中最多思绪交错的日子） -情人节！
TADANO'S SHOE LOCKER
（只野同学的鞋柜）
What is that?
那是怎样啊？
FLEES
（慌张）
GLANCE
（偷瞄）
TADANO CHECKS DEEPER THAN USUAL
（比平时看向鞋柜 更深处的只野同学）
NOTHING.
（空无一物）
TADANO CASUALLY CHECKS INSIDE HIS DESK
（悄悄检查抽屉的只野同学）
NOTHING
（空无一物）
Morning!
早安 哈啰
Happy Valentine's Day!
情人节快乐！
Here, Komi! Friend chocolate!
来 古见同学 给你友情巧克力！
Wow! You made it yourself?
好棒喔！古见同学自己做的吗？
Yay! Thank you!
太棒了！谢谢你！
Just a single Chirori Choco and my investment pays off big-time!
只要一颗滋丽巧克力 就换回这么大一包
It's a great day, Valentine's.
情人节真是不错的日子啊
INCORRIGIBLE…
（这家伙…）
Komi, good morning!
古见同学 早安！
She's here…!
（她出现了！）
I made some chocolates just for you!
我为你做了巧克力喔！
Take them!
收下吧！
OMINOUS
（不祥气息）
Yeah, eat it. Eat my face…
快吃下去吧 吃我的脸…
Lick me, suck me, eat me…
舔我、吸我、把我吃下肚…
And then I'll be a part of you forever…
我就会永远成为你身体的一部分…
SLIDES
（递出）
Y-Yamai?!
山井同学？
Hey, Yamai! Are you okay?
等等 山井同学 你还好吗？
Everyone's excited for Valentine's Day.
-还因情人节而乐昏了头 -山井同学！
Letting themselves be manipulated by an event created by a corporation.
明明是企业暗地里 操作出来的节日还随之起舞
Fools, all of them.
真是些愚民
For me, it's just another day.
不像我 就跟平常一样
Watch me behave as if nothing has changed!
看看跟平时完全相同的我！
Admire my normalcy. Bow to…
敬佩于我的平常心 并屈服于…
SUPER HAPPY
（开心到不行）
T-Thank you very much!
非常感谢你！
MAKERU'S VS. KOMI'S CHOCOLATES
（古见同学与真华留的 手工巧克力对决）
Sorry about yesterday. Take this as an apology.
昨天真抱歉啊 这是道歉巧克力
Are you giving true love chocolate to anyone?
我说你们 真爱巧克力要送谁啊？
Makoto Katai has come to school.
片居诚来学校了
Today is Valentine's Day.
今天是情人节
These days, even boys give each other so-called "rival chocolate."
听说最近似乎就连男生 都会互送“强敌巧克力”
I-I did bring some chocolates but I'm too shy to go first.
我是带了巧克力来啦 但自己开口送也太害羞了
I-I wonder if Tadano has something for me?
只野同学会不会主动送我啊？
He's in deep.
你是少女啊？
Chiarai, here.
地洗井 这给你
So you know, it's just obligatory.
我话说在前头 这是人情巧克力
I expect triple on White Day!
白色情人节你要回赠 比这好三倍的礼物！
Oh! Thank you!
好 谢啦！
Y-You should act happier!
你给我开心一点啦！
Don't move.
不许动
The thing at your back is the real thing.
抵在你背上的是真枪实弹
S-Stop.
快住手
BULLET-SHAPED CHOCOLATE
（子弹造型巧克力）
The real thing.
是真的呢
Hm? Valentine's Day?
什么？情人节？
What's that?
那是什么？
-I don't… need anything… -Chocolates? To someone you like?
-我不是在说我想要喔… -会送巧克力给喜欢的人啊
Wow.
这样啊
I have some brown sugar treats. Want some?
我有一些花林糖 你要吃吗？
All fantasies.
以上是妄想
Katai!
片居同学！
Sasaki! Are you trying to die?
佐佐木！你找死啊？
Go on, go!
好了 快去啦！
N-No! Everyone's looking!
才不要！大家都在看！
-I already called him. -KATAI IS SCARED
-我都已经叫他了 -（片居怕女生 觉得是在说坏话）
Um, uh. Here.
那个 给你这个
Y-You don't have to give me anything back.
不需要回礼没关系
W-What?!
什么？
-That's his response?! -PEOPLE WHO DIDN'T GET ANY
-收到巧克力还这么冷淡！ -（没收到巧克力的人们）
What is this package? I'm scared!
包装好的盒子中 装了什么啊？好可怕！
-So cool… -My mentor has chocolates? Why?
-好帅气… -师父要给我巧克力？为什么？
What does this mean?
这到底是什么意思？
DIDN'T GET CHOCOLATE FROM KOMI
（没收到古见同学的巧克力的人）
Yes, I shouldn't wait.
我懂了 果然不应该等待
I should be proactive!
自己主动出击比较好！
-You are so right! -MENTOR IN HIS HEART
-对吧？师父！ -（心灵师父 善交际同学）
You can do it!
加油喔！
DIDN'T GET CHOCOLATES FROM KOMI
（没收到古见同学的巧克力的人）
Are you giving chocolates to all your friends?
你是送巧克力给所有的朋友吗？
I-I see.
原来如此
AFTER SCHOOL
（放学后）
I-It's rival chocolate.
这是强敌巧克力
Thanks Katai.
谢谢你 片居同学
I don't have anything for you now.
但我现在没东西能回赠给你
I'll get you something on White Day.
我会在白色情人节送你的
Whi… That's like true love chocolate!
天啊！那根本是真爱巧克力嘛！
KOMI COULDN'T GIVE CHOCOLATE TO TADANO.
（无法把巧克力 送给只野同学的古见同学）
PEBBLE
（小石子）
On that day, Tadano was unconcerned.
那一天只野同学原本觉得稳操胜券
-I don't expect true love chocolates. -THIS MORNING: HITOHITO TADANO (17)
-我是不期待收到真爱巧克力啦 -（今早的只野仁人 17岁）
But I'll get some friend chocolates from my female friends, for sure.
但至少会收到 某个女生送的友情巧克力吧
Yes! Normally, Tadano is careful not to get too confident,
像这样即便是平常小心 不让自己得意忘形的只野同学
but look at him.
也落得这种下场
Valentine magic!
这就是情人节魔法！
But in reality…
但现实是…
Zero. Zero chocolates.
零个 零个巧克力
This number does not include chocolates from boys.
男生送的不列入这次的计算中
Sorry Katai, but that's how it is.
虽然对片居同学感到抱歉 但现实就是这样
Komi was a given, but even Onemine and Otori.
不只是古见同学 就连尾根峰同学还有尾鸡同学都是
Nothing from the girls he's friends with.
从交情好的女性朋友 那边一个都没收到
Unpopular! Tadano's unpopular!
不受欢迎！只野同学完全不受欢迎！
Get any chocolates?
收到巧克力了吗？
Hey!
哥哥！
Zero chocolates.
零个巧克力
The truth of this was enough stress to bring Tadano to his knees.
这种现实带来的精神上压力 已经足以让只野同学跪倒在地了
I didn't think you were the type?
哥哥 你原本就是这种类型吗？
Honey, what are you doing?
小仁 你在做什么？
Here's your chocolate.
这是给你的巧克力
Chocolates from Mom doesn't count!
妈妈送的巧克力当然也不列入计算！
Also, Tadano's mom calls him Honey!
而且只野同学的妈妈会用小名叫他！
Hey, cheer up.
我说你啊 打起精神来啦
Mom and I both gave you chocolates.
我跟妈妈都给你巧克力了
You got some from your friend too, didn't you?
你也有从朋友那边收到巧克力吧？
From… a boy…
从男生那边…
He got chocolates from a boy.
哥哥说他收到男生给的巧克力
Really? I don't know him, but he must be a nice boy.
是吗？虽然搞不太懂 但对方是个温柔的孩子呢
BZZZT
（察觉）
Hey, go buy some ice cream.
哥哥 去帮我买冰淇淋
Huh? No way. What a pain.
什么？才不要 好麻烦
It's cold out. Why ice cr--
话说天气这么冷 还要吃冰…
Just do it.
去就是了
Winter is a popular season for ice cream.
还有冬天已经 渐渐成为冰淇淋的热卖季节
It's warm inside so people crave ice cream.
屋里很温暖所以大家会想吃冰
Sales figures are rising every year.
实际上业绩也是年年增加
-Winter ice cream is a thing. -What?
-冰淇淋根本就成了冬天必吃食品 -什么啊？
TADANO GRUMBLED BUT DECIDED TO GO.
（有怨言但仍会出门买的只野同学）
Ooh it's cold.
天啊 好冷
BUMP
（撞）
Komi?
古见同学？
-Some bouillon too, Honey. -DOESN'T WANT KOMI TO HEAR
-小仁 你顺便买高汤回来 -（不想被她知道妈妈会叫他小名）
Oh, bouillon? Okay!
高汤吗？我知道了！
L-Let's go to the park!
总之我们先去公园吧！
Are you okay where I hit you with the door?
刚才撞到你的地方还好吗？
Oh, good. Sorry.
没事就好 真对不起
Anyway, what's up?
所以有什么事吗？
Today, uh.
今天还来找我
Chocolates? Is it chocolates?
是巧克力吗？要送巧克力吗？
MEETING NOTES FOR GARBAGE COLLECTION
（本月的班长会议记录 收垃圾时的注意事项）
What's this?
这个是…
"We had a student council meeting today.
“今天有班长会议
Najimi said to give this to you, since you didn't come."
驯染说因为你没来 要转交给你”
-Oh no! Thanks for bringing it to me. -WHY DIDN'T YOU COME?
-糟糕！很抱歉！让你跑一趟 -（只野同学怎么没来啦？）
-BYE THEN. -BOW
（那我先走了 鞠躬）
You're leaving?
你要回去了吗？
Uh, take care!
路上小心！
I don't know what I was expecting.
我到底在期待什么啊？
It's perfectly normal to not get anything.
没收到也是很正常的吧
It's Komi's choice whether she gives some to me or not.
要不要送也是古见同学的决定
Yeah! I expected too much!
没错 是我太过期待了！
What am I doing?
我到底在干吗啊？
Even so…
但是…
I hope she doesn't hate me…
希望我没被古见同学讨厌…
Ta… Tadano!
只…只野同学！
Yes?
请说
H-Here…
这个…
I-It's friend chocolate.
是友情巧克力
Of course! Of course it is!
那是当然的啊！
FOR TADANO
（只野同学收）
I'm embarrassed to say, but…
虽然有点丢脸 但是啊…
All day I've been wondering if I'd get some chocolates.
我今天一直在想会不会收到巧克力
You gave some to all of your friends after all.
古见同学似乎 送了巧克力给所有的朋友
But I didn't get any, and I gave up…
不过我没拿到 后来也不再期待了…
Um…
那个…
What am I trying to say?
我到底想说什么呢？
Anyway!
总之呢！
Getting chocolates from you makes me feel much…
能收到古见同学送的巧克力 远比我想象得…
happier than I imagined!
还要令人开心！
FLAP FLAP
（甩动）
T-Those chocolates…
其实…
T-They're the ones that…
那些是做得…
t-turned out best.
最成功的巧克力
Aw, you didn't have to. Thank you very much!
你不用特地这么做的 谢谢你！
POOF
（害羞）
DASH
（奔跑）
K-Komi?!
古见同学？
S-Suddenly? Komi?
太突然了吧 古见同学？
I-It's dark! I'll walk you home!
天色暗了！我送你回家啦！
Komi!
古见同学！
Subtitle translation by: Claire Tanaka
字幕翻译：吴敬美